Guide to the William F. Reeves Elevated Railroads Photograph Collection [1868]-1933 (bulk dates 1878-1906) PR 154
New-York Historical Society
William F. Reeves Elevated Railroads Photograph Collection
[1868]-1933
New-York Historical Society
PR 154
12.05 Linear feet (11 boxes)
Collection of photographs documenting the elevated railroads in New York City.
Provenance
300 photographs were a gift of the Estate of William F. Reeves, October 11, 1937.
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Historical Note
The implementation of a rapid transit system in New York City became an increasingly important issue during the 1850s and 1860s as the city spread northward and a growing number of people needed to be transported faster and more efficiently than horse-drawn vehicles would allow. New York's densely populated neighborhoods, the existing pedestrian and vehicle traffic, and Manhattan's long, narrow configuration necessitated a system that would run either above or below ground level. Numerous designs for both types of system were proposed to the state legislature during this time and public demand for rapid transit grew fervent.
In 1867 the city legislature approved a proposal for an experimental elevated cable railroad to be constructed on Greenwich Street between Dey and 29th Streets in Manhattan. Despite litigation brought by the omnibus companies, the elevated system evolved rapidly. By 1880, four steam-powered railroad lines ran through Manhattan, stretching from the Battery to the Harlem River, and carrying more than 175,000 passengers each day. Construction continued into the Bronx, linking the boroughs as the population swelled. The El, as the system was known from its earliest days, transformed the city during the second half of the nineteenth century. As the iron tracks dominated the landscape, the trains accelerated the pace of urban life, and in doing so facilitated a range of economic and social changes.
The elevated system reached it peak in 1921, with ridership reaching 374 million. However, the economic depression of the 1930s, changing political tides, and the expansion of the subway system soon brought about its demise. Service was discontinued on the Sixth Avenue Line in 1938 and the other lines followed shortly thereafter. With the demolition of the Third Avenue Line track in 1956, the era of New York's elevated railroads came to an end.
Sources:
Jackson, Kenneth T., ed., Encyclopedia of New York. London and New York: Yale University Press, 1995.
Reed, Robert C., The New York Elevated. South Brunswick and New York: A. S. Barnes and Co., 1978.
Reeves, William Fullerton, The First Elevated Railroads in Manhattan and the Bronx of the City of New York. New York: New-York Historical Society, 1936.
Stelter, Lawrence, By the El: Third Avenue and its El at mid-century. Flushing, New York: H&M Productions, 1995.
Biographical Note
William Fullerton Reeves was born in New York City in 1859. He was raised in the city and attended New York University. In 1880, he went to work as a civil engineer for the Manhattan Railway Company, the company that merged New York's independent elevated railroad lines into a unified system. Reeves continued to serve as an engineer when Manhattan Railway was taken over by the Interborough Rapid Transit Company in 1903. He spent the rest of his career with Interborough Rapid Transit, working on both the elevated railroads and the subway system. He specialized in the legal aspects of engineering and became an authority on contracts and easements. Reeves was a member of the American Society of Civil Engineers, the National Society of Professional Engineers, and the New York State Society of Professional Engineers, as well as a member of the Salmagundi Club in New York and an Associate Member of The New-York Historical Society.
The history of New York's elevated railroads was of great interest to Reeves. The city's earliest elevated structures were erected when he was a child, and he grew up during an era in which rapid transit was at the forefront of public affairs. He collected photographs, maps, and documents relating to the development of the elevated system. In 1935, he published "Elevated Railroads on Manhattan Island," a two-part article in the January and April volumes of the Quarterly Bulletin of the New-York Historical Society. Both parts were illustrated with images from his collection. The following year, the Society published a revised and augmented version of the article as a limited edition book entitled The First Elevated Railroads in Manhattan and the Bronx of the City of New York.
Williams Reeves died of a heart attack in his apartment at Hotel des Artistes, 1 West 67th Street, on September 18, 1936.
Scope and Content Note
The William F. Reeves Elevated Railroad Photograph Collection spans the period from ca. 1868 to 1933 and contains photographic prints of elevated railroads in New York City collected by William F. Reeves. The collection contains 235 photographs including albumen prints, cyanotypes, gelatin silver prints (mostly original early-twentieth century prints with some later copy prints,) and printing-out paper prints. In most cases the photographers have not been identified. The Estate of William F. Reeves donated these images to the New-York Historical Society in 1937 as part of a gift of approximately 300 photographs. The original donation was dispersed into various Print Room collections. The images in this collection were formerly included in the Geographic File (PR 020) and the Subject File (PR 068). The collection is arranged into six series by railroad line: Second Avenue Line; Third Avenue Line; Sixth Avenue Line; Ninth Avenue Line; Bronx Lines; and Miscellaneous Photographs. Although each Manhattan line is designated by the name of a numbered avenue, that avenue was not the only thoroughfare along which it traveled. Miscellaneous photographs include aerial photographs taken from a power plant and coal hoist on 74th Street near the East River.
Photographers represented throughout the collection include: James A. Bostick, N. L. Coe, Herman Cos, George P. Hall & Son, Instantaneous Photo Co., and J. Reid.
Arrangement
Photographs are arranged from south to north on the train route.
The collection is arranged into six series by railroad line:
Missing Title
Series I. Second Avenue Line ([1899]-1906)
Series II. Third Avenue Line (1876-1904)
Series III. Sixth Avenue Line ([1876]-1933)
Series IV. Ninth Avenue Line (1868-1905)
Series V. Bronx Lines (1883-1906)
Series VI. Miscellaneous Photographs (1924, undated)
Related Material at the Department of Prints, Photographs, and Architectural Collections
The New-York Historical Society holds copies of The First Elevated Railroads in Manhattan and the Bronx of the City of New York in the Library and the Print Room. The Library holds the manuscript for the book as well. Other N-YHS Print Room collections containing images of New York's elevated railroads include but are not limited to the Norvin H. Green Collection of Elevated Railroad Photographs (PR 023), the Subject File (PR 068), the Geographic File (PR 020), and the Architect and Engineer File (PR 003).
Mammoth plate; Cyanotypes; Gelatin silver prints.; Albumen prints.; Railroads, Elevated -- New York (State) -- New York.; Manhattan (New York, N.Y.); Bronx (New York, N.Y.); Urban transportation -- New York (State) -- New York.; Local transit -- New York (State) -- New York.; Instantaneous Photo View Company; Interborough Rapid Transit Company; Manhattan Railway Company; Reid, J. (Photographer); Suburban Rapid Transit Railway (New York, N.Y.); Bostick, James A.; Coe, N. L., (photographer); Hall, George P., 1832-1900
- Series I: Second Avenue Line
  Scope and Contents note
  Series I. Second Avenue Line is made up of sixteen photographs (ca. 1899-1906) of the elevated line that ran from Chatham Square to 129th Street in Manhattan. The Second Avenue Line was the last of the four Manhattan elevated lines to be constructed, beginning service in 1880. An 1886 mammoth plate albumen print shows the curving tracks at the 129th Street Terminus. Two prints in the series illustrate the relationship between the tracks and buildings, one an 1899 view looking down at the tracks near 42nd Street, the other a 1905 view of the tracks over Allen Street, looking north from Division Street. The latter image is part of a set of ten photographs from 1905 that also show street life under the tracks along Division Street. A 1905 view captures an electric train at the 34th Street station, providing evidence of the system-wide conversion from steam to electricity that occurred 1901-1903. A 1906 image shows a train at the 80th Street Station, the conductor's head appearing out of a window as a man in a bowler hat (who may be William Reeves) watches from the platform.
  Photographs are arranged from south to north on the train route. The number of prints in each folder is noted in parentheses.
  - Division Street (9 prints), 1905 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - South of 50th Street (3 prints), [1899]-1905 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 3)
  - North of 50th Street (3 prints), 1886-1906 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 4)
    General note
    See also Box 10, Folder 41
- Series II: Third Avenue Line
  Series II. Third Avenue Line contains twenty-nine photographs dating from 1876 to 1904. The Third Avenue Line began service in 1878 and ran from South Ferry to the Harlem River in Manhattan. An early-twentieth century copy print of a photograph from 1876 shows a view from a rooftop looking north from 96th Street before the construction of the tracks. Another copy photograph of an image from ca. 1878 shows a group of women and children on a lawn at Whitehall Street with the El behind them. Two mammoth plate albumen prints from 1882 show the City Hall Station and include the Manhattan terminus of the Brooklyn Bridge, still under construction. City Hall Station appears again in an 1884 albumen print. Different sized albumen prints from 1882 show stations at 9th Street and 23rd Street. The tracks and terminal yards at 98th-99th Streets are shown in two mammoth plate prints and one early-twentieth century copy print of a photograph from ca. 1895-1900. Two additional mammoth plate albumen prints that show Third Avenue between 26th and 27th Streets ca. 1890, have stamps and notations that suggest they were used as evidence in legal proceedings. Northern sections of the line are visible in a group of six cyanotypes from about 1898 showing views from 99th Street and the yards at 129th Street used by the Third Avenue and Second Avenue Lines. Three prints from 1900 show the tracks at Third Avenue and 76th Street. Another set of three prints, these from 1904, show improvements, mainly at ground-level, to the station at the Chatham Square, where the Third Avenue Line was linked to the Second Avenue Line. An 1878 photograph shows the original Chatham Square station and the tracks before work on the Second Avenue Line began.
  - City Hall Station and south (2 prints), 1882-1884 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 5)
    See also Box 10, Folder 42
  - Chatham Square (4 prints), 1878-1904 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 6)
  - City Hall north to 10th Street (3 prints), 1882-1896 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 7)
  - 10th Street north to 25th Street (4 prints), 1882 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 8)
  - 25th Street north to 50th Street (2 prints), 1890 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 9)
  - 50th Street north to 98th Street (4 prints), 1876-1900 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 10)
  - 98th to 99th Street Terminal Yards (3 prints), 1882-[1900] (Offsite-box 2, Folder 11)
  - 99th Street Terminal Yards [Cyanotypes] (6 prints), [1898] (Offsite-box 2, Folder 12)
- Series III: Sixth Avenue Line
  Series III. Sixth Avenue Line contains 136 photographs that span the period from ca. 1876 to 1933. The Sixth Avenue Line ran from Morris Street to one terminus at 59th Street and also had a branch that turned west at 53rd Street, then headed north on Ninth Avenue to 110th Street where it curved east onto Eighth Avenue and continued north to 155th Street. The Sixth Avenue Line began service to 59th Street in 1878 with the northern section of the route opening the following year.
  Images of the line below 59th Street include two 1880s mammoth plate albumen prints of the station at 34th Street, and another of the station at 42nd Street, that depict the decorative architecture of the station buildings. In contrast to the ornate stations, the dark spaces created beneath the tracks are evident in a series of three albumen prints of Sixth Avenue from 42nd Street to 43rd Street. Among the businesses visible is the studio of photographer James A. Bostick, suggesting, perhaps, that he made these images. A set of nine gelatin silver prints from 1899 documents the tracks in lower Manhattan, each one captioned with text describing problematic structural details. Two cyanotype views from 1902 show the tracks at the South Ferry Station, which by that time was the southern hub of the elevated lines. A silver gelatin print, taken by Herman Cos in 1913, shows the stairway to the 50th Street Station.
  Above 59th Street, a series of mammoth-plate albumen prints document the construction of the tracks from 97th Street to 112th Street. Two of these, dated February and April 1891, show the same view under the tracks both before and after the paving of Ninth Avenue. Two gelatin silver prints from 1933 show the tracks at 63rd Street. Two early-twentieth century copy prints of photographs from ca. 1876 show early test trains on the tracks between 59th and 60th Streets. The dramatic curve at 110th Street is captured in a series of mammoth-plate albumen prints from 1879. The 100th Street station is shown in cyanotypes from 1903 as well as in a few silver gelatin prints from 1933. The construction of the yards at 155-159th Streets, used by both the Sixth Avenue Line and the Ninth Avenue Line, appears in several cyanotypes dated 1902 and 1903. A 1904 print showing cars at the yards has the notation "Cottington vs. Interborough R. T. Co." on the verso. An album from 1902-1903 holds sixty photographs which document the construction of the Inspection Building at 159th Street.
  - Subseries I: Below 59th Street
    - South Ferry Terminal (2 prints), 1902 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 13)
    - South Ferry north to 3rd Street (9 prints), 1888-[1899] (Offsite-box 3, Folder 14)
    - 3rd Street north to 10th Street (4 prints), 1877-[1899] (Offsite-box 3, Folder 15)
    - 10th Street north to 40th Street (4 prints), 1881-1889 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 16)
      See also Box 10, Folder 43
    - 40th Street north to 59th Street (4 prints), 1888-1913 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 17)
  - Subseries II: Above 59th Street
    - 59th Street north to 70th Street (7 prints), [1876]-1933 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 18)
    - 70th Street north to 80th Street (2 prints), 1891 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 19)
    - 80th Street north to 90th Street (3 prints), 1891-1933 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 20)
    - 90th Street north to 100th Street (9 prints), 1891-1905 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 21-23)
      See also Box 10, Folder 44
    - 100th Street north to 110th Street (4 prints), 1878-1897 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 24)
    - 110th Street Station (6 prints), 1903-1933 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 25)
    - 110th Street Curve (3 prints), 1879 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 26)
    - 110th Street north to 155th Street (3 prints), 1879-1902 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 27)
    - Terminal and Yards, 155-159th Streets (8 prints), 1902-1904 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 28)
    - Inspection Building, 159th Street (1 album), 1902-1903 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 29)
- Series IV: Ninth Avenue Line
  Series IV. Ninth Avenue Line contains twenty-three prints (ca. 1868 to 1905) of the first elevated railroad line in New York City. Service began in 1869 on a route from Dey Street to 29th Street and eventually the line ran from Battery Park to 59th Street. Images of tracks on Ninth Avenue above 59th Street are included in the collection in Series III, because the route of the Sixth Avenue Line included the stretch of Ninth Avenue from 53rd Street to 110th Street.
  Images of the Ninth Avenue Line include a series of albumen prints from 1868-1869 showing the construction of tracks along Greenwich Street. An early-twentieth century copy print of a photograph from 1869 shows the first cable propelled passenger car at the 29th Street Station, with a horse-drawn omnibus below the tracks. The construction of the second elevated structure on Ninth Avenue, built on the West Side of the street, appears in a print from 1876, looking north from West 46th Street. A series of four prints by N. L. Coe from 1898 vividly illustrate the close proximity of the tracks to buildings at the Desbrosses Street Station. An 1891 albumen print preserves the view of the tracks at Greenwich Street and Morris Street where the Ninth Avenue Line merged with the Sixth Avenue Line. Two images from about 1905 show the tracks over Greenwich Street near Dey Street.
  - Battery Park north to Vestry Street (10 prints), 1868-1905 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 30)
  - Desbrosses Street Station (5 prints), 1898 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 31)
  - Watts Street north to 14th Street (2 prints), 1869, undated (Offsite-box 7, Folder 32)
  - 14th Street north to 59th Street (5 prints), 1869-1877 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 33)
    See also Box 10, Folder 45
- Series V: Bronx Lines
  Series V. Bronx Lines spans the period from ca. 1883 to 1906 and contains eighteen images relating to the elevated trains in the Bronx. Elevated railroad service in the Bronx began in 1886. A set of three images documents the construction of the bridge and tracks built over the Harlem River in 1883-1884. Mammoth plate albumen prints from 1884 by J. Reid show stations and track structures of the Suburban Rapid Transit Company, the company that built the elevated railroads in the Bronx. A series of four prints from about 1906 show the tracks over Third Avenue. A 1903 print by George P. Hall & Son shows a train car elevator at the Bronx Park Yards.
  - 131st Street Bridge north to 179th Street (11 prints), 1883-1906 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 34-35)
    See also: Box 10, Folder 46
  - Third Avenue and 179th Street Yards (5 prints), 1900-1912 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 36)
  - Bronx Park Yards at E. 193rd Street (1 print), 1903 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 37)
- Series VI: Miscellaneous Photographs
  Series VI. includes photographs which are mostly uncaptioned and undated. These are mainly images of railroad trains and equipment, or railway men. One print shows a twentieth-century copy photograph of a plan for an elevated railway, proposed in 1872 by Civil War General Franz Sigel. Another photograph shows several men, including William Reeves, watching as ground was broken in January of 1924 for the removal of the 42nd Street Elevated Spur. There are also a series of mounted photographs showing aerial and street views of the area around 74th Street along the East River in 1905, and several 1904 photographs of excavations in Chatham Square for the elevated railway.
  - Plans, undated (Offsite-box 9, Folder 38)
  - Portraits, 1924, undated (Offsite-box 9, Folder 39)
  - Trains, undated (Offsite-box 9, Folder 40)
  - Photographs, Chatham Square Excavation, 1904 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 47)
  - Photographs taken from coal hoist on 74th Street and Exterior Avenue (now FDR), 1905 October 26 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 48)
  - Aerial photographs taken from Powerhouse on 75th Street and Avenue A, 1905 October 26 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 49-50)
  - Photographs, street-level, taken from 71st and 74th Street, 1905 October 27 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 51)
  - George P. Hall photograph of old York Street gate, Brooklyn, circa 1900 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 52)
- Oversize
  - From Series I.Second Avenue Line
    - 129th Street Terminal, 1886 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 41)
  - From Series II. Third Avenue Line
    - City Hall Station, 1882 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 42)
  - From Series III. Sixth Avenue Line
    - Below 59th Street
      - 33rd Street Station (2 prints), [1889] (Offsite-box 10, Folder 43)
      - 42nd Street Station, [1889] (Offsite-box 10, Folder 43)
    - Above 59th Street
      - Ninth Avenue between 97th and 98th, 1898 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 44)
      - Ninth Avenue between 98th and 99th Streets, 1879 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 44)
      - Ninth Avenue and 101st Street, 1878-1879 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 44)
  - From Series IV. Ninth Avenue Line
    - Ninth Avenue and 42nd Street, 1876 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 45)
  - From Series V. Bronx Lines
    - Willis Avenue and 132nd Street Bridge, 1885 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 46)